A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Community and Resource Development, Acting Director, Office Files of Carl Anthony FA507
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Community and Resource Development, Acting Director, Office Files of Carl Anthony
1998-2006, bulk 2001-2006
2001-2006
Rockefeller Archive Center
Anthony, Carl
Ford Foundation
FA507
3.04 Cubic Feet 8 letter document boxes.
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development (CRD); and Human Development and Reproductive Health. Carl Anthony joined the Ford Foundation as a Program Officer within the Assets Program's CRD Unit in 2001. In 2003, he became Deputy Director of Community and Resource Development and in 2004, Acting Director. As Program Officer, Anthony directed the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI), the Foundation's grantmaking portfolio in equitable and sustainable community development. He also participated in making substantial cross-portfolio investments in Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs, singular RED). The Office Files of Carl Anthony span in date from 1999 to 2006 and primarily document his work as Program Officer. The bulk of the collection consists of grantee files, primarily of SMCI and RED grant recipients. These files contain correspondence, project updates, conference materials, products of Ford-funded research, and background information about grantees and projects. The collection also contains files on trips, conferences and meetings Anthony attended in his capacity as Program Officer and Acting Director.
Arrangement
Arranged into 5 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) Files, 1998-2006
Series II. Regional Equity Demonstration (RED) Files, 1999-2006
Series III. Grant-Related Files, 2001-2005
Series IV. Trips, Conferences and Meetings, 2001-2005
Series V. Writings, 2006
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Carl Anthony span in date from 1999 to 2006 and primarily document his work as Program Officer managing the Community and Resource Development Unit portfolio on regional equity and smart growth. The bulk of the collection consists of grantee files, primarily of recipients of grants under the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) and the Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs). The collection also contains files on trips, conferences and meetings he attended in his capacity as Program Officer and Acting Director at Ford.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Philadelphia, Carl Anthony received a PhD in Architecture and Urban Planning from Columbia University. Between 1989 and 2001, he served as founding Executive Director of Urban Habitat, one of the nation's oldest environmental and economic justice organizations.
In 2001, he joined the Ford Foundation as a Program Officer within the Assets Program's Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit. As Program Officer, he directed the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI), the Foundation's grantmaking portfolio in equitable and sustainable community development. SMCI sought to alleviate concentrated poverty resulting from public policies and business practices that promoted economically segregated communities and ecologically unsustainable growth. It supported grantees engaged in a wide range of work, including research and discussions on urban sprawl and smart growth; leadership and capacity building; policy development; and strategic communication influencing more equitable regional resource allocation.
As a CRD Unit program officer, Mr. Anthony also participated in making substantial cross-portfolio investments in Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs, singular RED). REDs were practical learning applications and demonstrations of the Foundation's regional approach to community development and urban revitalization. Then CRD Unit Director Cynthia Miller originally initiated RED as a unit-wide initiative designed to foster substantial cross-portfolio investments focused on racial justice and social equity in the City of Camden, New Jersey and its surrounding communities. REDs were initiated at four other locations: Richmond, California; Baltimore, Maryland; Detroit, Michigan; and Atlanta, Georgia. In Camden, New Jersey, where the majority of grant funds were invested, the Foundation promoted its regional equity agenda through targeted investments in the areas of real estate development, employment opportunities, public sector capacity, and civic engagement. Mr. Anthony continued the RED initiative through his tenure as CRD Unit Deputy Director in 2003 and Acting Director in 2004. With the selection of Suzanne Siskel as CRD Unit Director in 2006, RED came under the management of the single grant portfolio, SMCI.
In 2006, Mr. Anthony left the Foundation to become a Visiting Scholar and Ford Foundation Senior Fellow in the Department of Geography at the University of California Berkeley.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program brought together four previously separate Foundation programs in Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Reproductive Health and Population, and Program Related Investments. It supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development; and Human Development and Reproductive Health. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program.
- Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) Files, 1998-2006; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of subject files documenting the work of Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) grantees. Files are arranged alphabetically by name of grantee or project and contain correspondence, conference materials, products of Ford-funded research, and background information about grantees and projects. The bulk of correspondence pertains to project updates and conference information grantees sent to Mr. Anthony. Files on conferences held by grantees, grantmaking partners or the Ford Foundation that Mr. Anthony kept with his SMCI files are included in this series. Additional conference files can be found in Series IV: Trips, Conferences and Meetings.
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Memoranda Re: Meeting, Conference Call Agenda, 2004 February 17-2005 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Papers on Race and Regional Equity, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Reception and Workshop at the NAACP National Convention, Philadelphia, PA, 2004 July 10-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Atlanta Neighborhood Development Partnership (ANDP) -- Correspondence, Published Report on Mixed Income and Mixed Use Communities, 2002 April 8-2004 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bay Area Council -- Memoranda Re: Background for Conference Call, Report on Bay Area Family of Funds, 2003 January 12-2004 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Center for Community Change -- Correspondence, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Collins Center for Public Policy -- Correspondence Re: Building a Region of Strong Neighborhoods in South Florida, 2003 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Commonweal -- "Conversations with Advocates of Fair Growth" (interviews by Steve Lerner) (1 of 2), 2004 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commonweal -- "Conversations with Advocates of Fair Growth" (interviews by Steve Lerner) (2 of 2), 2004 October (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commonweal -- "Smart Growth/Fair Growth: Building Mixed-Income Communities" (report by Steve Lerner) (1 of 2), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commonweal -- "Smart Growth/Fair Growth: Building Mixed-Income Communities" (report by Steve Lerner) (2 of 2), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Earth House -- Information Kits on SMCI, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Earth House -- Internal Communications Audit Summary Report, Interview Notes, 2002 December-2003 May (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications for SMCI, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Meeting Notes, Charts, Planning Report, Email, 2002 December-2003 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Plan (separated), 2003 September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Work Plans and Reports, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Justice Resource Center -- Correspondence, Report on Strategies for Achieving Environmental, Racial and Economic Justice, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ferris, Deeohn -- SMCI Project on African American Perspectives on Regionalism, Regional Equity and Smart Growth, 1998-2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gamaliel Foundation -- National Leadership Assembly "Eyes on the Prize: Coalitions to Win Metro Equity" -- Agenda, Conference Book, 2002 December 5-7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University Center on Sustainable Growth -- Report and Research on Sustainable Metropolitan Communities, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Good Jobs First -- Correspondence, Clippings Re: Smart Growth and Unions, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Good Jobs First -- Monograph and Summary Report of Interviews of Labor Union Leaders on Smart Growth, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Greater Baltimore Urban League -- Correspondence Re: Transportation Project, Comprehensive Social Equity Study Update, etc., 2002 June 3-2004 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Harvard University Civil Rights Project -- Round Table on Transportation Equity -- Agenda, Discussion Questions, Participant List, Concept Paper, Invitation, 2003 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Institute on Race and Poverty -- Conference on Race and Regionalism, Minneapolis, MN -- Correspondence, Conference Book, Summary, 2005 May 6-7 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Institute on Race and Poverty -- Correspondence, Papers on Race, Regional Equity and Urban Sprawl, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - InterValley Project (IVP) -- Correspondence, Meeting Agenda, Background on Issue Campaigns and Brownfield Organizing, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Metro Organization for Racial and Economic Equity -- Summit on Racism and Metropolitan Dynamics: Organizing for Statewide Solutions -- Agenda, Background, 2003 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Economic Development and Law Center (NEDLC) -- Concept Paper on Community Capital Investment Initiative (CCII), 2004 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Neighborhood Coalition (NNC) -- Correspondence, Background on NNC, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Vacant Properties Campaign -- Research and Policy Forum to Identify Campaign Priorities Creating Opportunity from Abandonment, Washington, DC, 2004 July 28-29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - PolicyLink -- Advancing Regional Equity: Second Annual Summit on Equitable Development, Social Justice and Smart Growth, Philadelphia, PA, 2005 May 23-25 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - PolicyLink and Funders' Network for Smart Growth and Livable Communities -- Promoting Regional Equity: A National Summit on Equitable Development, Social Justice and Smart Growth, Los Angeles, CA, 2002 November 17-19 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Redefining Progress -- Correspondence, Background on Common Assets Program, Sustainability Indicators Program, etc., 2001 October-2003 December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA) -- 14th Annual Regional Assembly, New York, NY -- Reports, Lists of Speakers, Participants and Workshops, 2004 April 16 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA) -- Civic Alliance to Rebuild Downtown New York -- Meeting Notes, Resolutions, Prospectus Outline, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rochester (City of) -- Rochester Conversation on Mid-Size Cities -- Correspondence, Agenda, Published Summary, 2002 November 12-13 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Surface Transportation Policy Project -- Correspondence, Interim Report, Draft Policy Statement, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Torrice Productions -- Correspondence Re: Funding Production of Documentary "The New Metropolis", 2003 October-November (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Transportation and Land Use Coalition (TALC) -- Correspondence, Narrative on Great Communities Initiative, 2002 October-2006 June (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Working Partnerships USA -- Correspondence from Amy B. Dean Re: Project Support, Move to Chicago, etc., 2003 May (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Regional Equity Demonstration (RED) Files, 1999-2006; II
  This series consists of files documenting the Ford Foundation Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit's Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs). Although there are a few files on other RED project locations, files on the RED project in Camden, New Jersey constitute the bulk of the series. Camden RED files consist of correspondence, meeting materials, proposals, and background information on Camden, grantees and projects. Several files document various RED staff meetings as well as the Foundation's partnership and collaboration with The Reinvestment Fund (TRF), the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) and the Annie E. Casey Foundation.
  In addition, there are three files pertaining to the work of consultant David Rusk. Mr. Rusk prepared activity reports, recommendations, and papers in his role as advisor to the CRD Unit in national strategies for regional reform and as a resource for Ford grantees in Atlanta, Baltimore, Detroit, Philadelphia and Camden.
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation -- Consultative Session on Responsible Relocation, 2005 March 16-17 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation and the Camden Development Collaborative -- Correspondence, Camden Funders Report, Background, 2000-2006 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Camden Churches Organized for the People, Inc. (CCOP) -- Correspondence, Background, Presentation Given During Site Visit, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Camden Redevelopment Agency Reorganization Proposal, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Concordia LLC -- Proposal, Report, Appendix of Meeting Summaries and Interviews, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Council of New Jersey Grantmakers -- Correspondence, Meeting and Convening Materials on Regional Equity Project in Southern Jersey, Proposal, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Energy Programs Consortium -- Weatherization, Rehab and Asset Preservation (WRAP) Partnership -- Background, 2004 January 15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hatcher Group -- Correspondence, Summary Recommendations for Communicating Ford Foundation Work in Camden, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invest in Camden Day Conference, Camden, NJ -- Agenda, Brochures on Camden Organizations and Development Projects, 2004 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Prepared for Meetings with Ford Foundation, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New Jersey Institute for Social Justice -- Meeting on Regional Equity, Civil Rights and the Low-Income Housing Tax Credit Program -- Correspondence, Agenda, Background Paper, 2003 May 6 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New Jersey Regional Coalition (NJRC) -- Briefing on New Jersey Political Environment and Legislation, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - PolicyLink -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Regional Equity/Equitable Development Strategy, 2002 April 29 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Regional and Neighborhood Equity Project (RNEP) Meeting (7/28-29/2005) -- Agenda, Correspondence, Background, 2005 June-July (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - RED -- Background and Descriptions of the Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit and RED, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - RED -- Ford Foundation Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit Site Visit to Camden, 2002 November 21 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - RED -- Report to the Ford Foundation on the Camden Environmental Justice Scan, 2004 January 16 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - RED -- Research and Reports on Camden, NJ, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - RED Meetings -- Agendas, Memoranda, Notes, Background, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - RED Program Officer Meeting -- Summary, RED FAP Overview, 2004 April 20-May 11 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - RED Staff Planning Meetings and Retreat -- Agenda, Strategic Plan, Retreat Notes, 2004 September-2005 May (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - RED Stakeholders Meetings (9/30/2003 and 11/20/2003) -- Meeting Summary, Invitation, Agenda (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reinventing America's Older Communities Conference, Philadelphia, PA -- Agenda, Draft Problem Statement Re: Small Weak Market Cities, 2004 January 14-16 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Reinvestment Fund (TRF) -- Correspondence, Paper, Background on Project Based Regionalism in Camden, NJ, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Richmond Initiative -- Project Overview, Analysis of Proposed Just Cause/Fair Rent Ordinance for Richmond by Urban Habitat, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Rusk, David -- Consultant Activity Reports, Speeches, 1999-2004 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rusk, David -- Draft Paper on Measuring Regional Equity, Summary of Paper, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Rusk, David -- The People's Summit for Regional Equity -- Program, Participant List, Presentation, 2003 June 27 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - The Trust for Public Land -- Advisory Council Meeting Minutes, Background on Camden, NJ, 2003 January 9-10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance and Community (CJTC) -- Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Minutes, Summary, Background, Participant Bios, 2004 February 24-25 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance and Community (CJTC) -- Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Report, Background, Participant Bios, 2004 October 3-5 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance and Community (CJTC) - Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Report, Comments, Participants List, 2006 January 17-18 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Urban Habitat -- Overview of Strategic Communication Needs and Transcript of Interview Between Carl Anthony, Juliet Ellis and Angela Glover-Blackwell, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Grant-Related Files, 2001-2005; III
  This series consists of files relating to grants Mr. Anthony managed within his program area of regional equity and smart growth. Mr. Anthony kept these files as part of his General Files. They are maintained as a separate series because it is unclear whether these grants were issued as part of the SMCI or RED initiatives. Files contain correspondence and memoranda along with attached proposals, meeting notes, agenda and background materials regarding proposed or then-ongoing grant activity. One highlight is a file that documents Mr. Anthony's involvement in the creation of the Funder's Network, a resource for foundations, nonprofit organizations and other partners working to address problems resulting from suburban sprawl and urban disinvestment.
  - The Funders' Network -- IRS Agreement, Papers on Smart Growth Issues, Meeting Notes, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Living Cities: The National Community Development Initiative -- Agenda, Email Correspondence, Discussion Paper on Shaping Public Policy (1 of 2), 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Living Cities -- Meeting Book with Agenda, Memoranda, Background (2 of 2), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Public Sector Mapping Project -- Memoranda, Papers on Workforce Development Perspective, Homeland Security, etc., 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Regional Equity -- Notes, Agenda, PowerPoint, Program Officer Memorandum, 2003 April-June (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Selecting and Working with Public Relations Firms: A Guide for Grantmakers", 2003 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sexual and Reproductive Health -- Memoranda, Background, Human Rights Meeting Minutes and Materials, 2002-2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Study on Urbanization, Environment and Development in Africa -- Background Papers, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Trips, Conferences and Meetings, 2001-2005; IV
  This series consists of files Mr. Anthony maintained of various conferences and meetings he attended on behalf of the Foundation. Files contain correspondence, agenda, notes, and background information for conferences held by other philanthropies such as the Land Bank Authority Forum in Flint, Michigan; conferences held with some Ford Foundation support such as the Funder's Network Conference in New Orleans; and internal Foundation events such as the Environment and Development Affinity Group workshop in China. A few files document meetings held at the Foundation building in New York, including the Ford Foundation Community Benefits Roundtable. There are also records of Mr. Anthony's travels for Foundation-related reasons such as his site visit to the Center for Heirs' Property Preservation in Charleston, South Carolina.
  - Advancing Regional Equity: Second Annual Summit on Equitable Development, Social Justice and Smart Growth, Philadelphia, PA -- Agenda, Background, 2005 May 21-25 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The African American Conversations: Black Life-New Vision -- Synopsis, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism, Oct 4, 2005, Detroit, MI, 2002-2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - African American Leadership Commission (AALC) Meeting, Chicago, IL -- Agenda, Background, 2005 June 15-17 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Center for Heirs' Property Preservation Site Visit, Charleston, SC, 2001 October 26-30 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Conversations on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting, Los Angeles, CA -- Agenda, Background, 2005 June 5-7 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Environment and Development Affinity Group Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa -- Program, Background, Reports, 2002 January 21-25 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Environment and Development Affinity Group Meeting, Ooty, India -- Meeting Book, Background (1 of 2), 2004 November 4-9 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Environment and Development Affinity Group Meeting, Ooty, India (2 of 2), 2004 November 4-9 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Environment and Development Affinity Group Workshop, Shangri-La, China -- Program, Notes, Background (1 of 2), 2003 October 27-29 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Environment and Development Affinity Group Workshop, Shangri-La, China (2 of 2), 2003 October 27-29 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation Community Benefits Round Table -- Agenda, Presenters, Background, Notes, 2004 June 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings on Mixed-Income Housing and Hardest-to-House Population -- Summary, Notes, 2002 August 26-2003 January 13 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Program Division Joint Worldwide Meeting -- Rapporteur's Report, 2003 January 29 (Box 7, Folder 7)